Okay, we are now one to call to order the regular meeting of the Miami City Council for today's
day.
Item two on the agenda is Proclamation declaring May 17, 2016, Greg Smith Day.
I've got a proclamation I'd like to read to you.
I could pretty well express as everything that we feel about Greg.
Whereas May is brain cancer awareness month and whereas Mayor Rudy Schultz and the Miami City
Council believe it is important to recognize citizens who distinguish themselves by various
means and who have made significant contributions in our community.
And whereas the Miami City Council believes that Greg Smith is such an individual or the
of being recognized for his significant contributions to this community and whereas Greg was
an honorable family man and especially proud of his son, Spencer, and Sutton.
Whereas Greg was a lifelong member of Miami First Baptist Church where he served as
Deacon and Treasurer as well as taught youth Sunday school.
Whereas Greg graduate is valedictorian in Miami High School class of 95 and continue to
his education at Oklahoma State University, the Oklahoma State University, graduating with a
degree in finance in 1999.
And whereas Greg attended the University of Oklahoma School of Law, graduating with his
jurist doctorate in 2004, it was a member of the American Bar Association and the Ottawa
County Bar Association and whereas Greg Smith has provided support and leadership throughout
the city of Miami in various civic and charitable organizations including but not limited
to chairman of the Miami Downtown Redevelopment Authority, served on the Miami Economic Development
Services Board, Miami Public Schools and Richmond Foundation and a member of the Miami
Area Chamber of Commerce as well as coaching youth basketball and baseball.
And whereas in 2012, the General Records selected him as one of 40 achievers under 40 and
whereas Greg was the recipient of the head for the cure keeping the faith award for the Kansas
City Area in August of 2014 and whereas being a father friend and mentor to his two sons
Spencer and Sutton was one of Greg's greatest honors, matched only by the joy of being
Julius husband and friend and confident on it.
Now therefore, be it resolved that mere shelves in the Miami City Council do hereby declare Tuesday
May 17th, 2016 as Greg Smith day within the city of Miami and witness where I have here
on to set my hand and cause the seal of the city of Miami to be fixed on the 17th day of
Miami and if you would come up please I have some copies that I would like to present
Julie and I know we have the larger frame.
Okay, item number three is public input and unscheduled personal parenthesis if there's anyone in the audience that wishes to address the
council on any of the agenda items.
Item number four is a consent agenda staff is recommending item of five through 11 to be placed on the consent agenda.
There's no discussion on any of those items.
I have an entertain the motion.
There's no objection.
I'll make that motion there.
And second.
Second.
Roll call.
Johnson.
Aye.
Lewis.
Forester.
Aye.
Item number 12.
Is a fire sales tax budgeting amending a purchasing policy.
Jill.
Back in 2003 voters approved proposition number two that allowed the Ottawa county, a lot of the county to
Levy of one 10 sales tax, which would be divided equally among the fire departments in Ottawa county.
The purpose is was pretty broad.
It, it's as purchase of equipment, general operation maintenance, training, new construction improvements to buildings.
So it's very pretty broad.
Our charter states that claims along with related supporting documentation shall be submitted to the city council for payment authorization.
Because these monies are designated to the city for fire protection.
We feel like a policy is is probably what we need to have.
So we make sure that the money runs through you guys are approving the purchases.
I did earlier today in the special meeting.
I showed you their proposed budget for next year.
This policy would be part of that.
It actually formalizes how the city is going to.
Budget the money approved for spending.
And men's a budget and then just the process on how that works and how everybody.
How their what their responsibilities of their department will be.
I wrote the policy and then I let Chief Klein and Captain Wright take a look at it.
I'm not sure if they showed it to others.
I'm sure they probably did.
We have a policy review committee.
I had them look at it.
I also had legal look at it.
So if you guys want to talk about it specifically.
We can.
If you have any questions.
I'd also share this with Ottawa county.
Yes.
Just a couple of questions, Jill, when a claim is presented to the council, it's for payment
authorization, but the funds are actually held by the county, is that correct?
That is correct.
So they will actually go through the process, too.
Yes.
That's what I thought.
I just want to make sure.
It sounds like we'll be paying the bill, but we're not, we're just saying the council authorized.
Yes.
They did budget.
So if they, like they, one of the things on the budget was the SCBAs.
So if they're ready to purchase them, I've created a form, they'll fill out the form.
We'll put it on the agenda.
You guys all prove it, it'll probably be on consent unless you want to pull it out to talk
about it.
You guys will prove it, they'll go out and purchase them, they'll bring the invoice, and that
form a proof form, because there's a place for you to sign, to finance, and then finance will contact
auto-accounting and ask them to pay that invoice.
So that'll be on a reimbursement basis, and that way, they'll actually pay the vendor
direct.
Okay.
How many fart apartments are in auto-accounting?
Wow.
I don't know that.
I wonder how many of this is going to fund?
The sales tax amount.
Is there no?
When you count the Tribal's apartments, I think nine cents right.
It does sound right.
Yeah.
We get the, what they normally get, very conservative is about $2,000 to $2,100 a month.
But that's what the city's apartments are.
That's the city's portion.
Right.
But as you we looked at earlier, it's the city portion, the other departments are getting there.
They're the same amount, really.
Did you understand that?
Yes.
I'm not sure if that was what you were asked or not.
So it made that eight cents made, it provides funding to eight or nine different departments.
Yes.
But we looked at what's just for the city.
I think it's great.
Great idea.
Any other questions or comments?
We have a motion.
Motion approved.
And a second?
A second.
Opa.
Western.
I.
Johnson.
Aye.
Forster.
Lewis.
I.
OK.
Adam 13.
Naming.
New animal shelter facility.
Dean?
Well, you're on our last minute.
There was a discussion.
I think raised by council member Johnson about naming rights or something for the
animal shelter.
After there's been a proposed name for this shelter, a name that's been thought about.
And that's naming it after Mrs. Kehili and also former Mayor Ketcher, that they were both very
ardent supporters for this, did a lot for animals in this community.
And we kind of talk about it and everything, but I just thought it might be better just to say,
would we want to name this the Ketcher Kehili animal shelter?
and possibly bring it as a resolution at a later time,
throw that name out there.
If anybody has another suggestion or an idea,
they might be able to share it with you,
but it seems that it's better to just start with
a suggestion rather than having things
that might be floating out there.
But I know that their actions and their work
predated me and my coming back to my end of
but what I'm seeing as an end result
has been very good for this community
and it seems like it'd be very worthwhile.
So what you're basically, we're making the
public aware that this is a proposed name.
Yes.
And if there are any other suggestions
that they should contact their council member
or the city directly with any other suggestion.
But after a period of time,
if not, I think we should bring you a resolution
we should just name it after these two people.
And we, I know we've been asked us a few times
by meal, but do we have a projected completion date?
August.
Okay.
August 15th is what we're concerned about.
Okay, so be nice to have this result
by the time we do the ribbon cutting.
Right.
So what's plan on resolving it?
Sometime, first meeting in July.
So if you have any suggestions,
members of the public, please come forward with them.
Send.
Okay.
Can I ask a question?
Who fought with the second name?
Can he read?
It was in a digital order.
She was a long time volunteer that kept
the one on a digital central,
going almost single and late for very long time.
Yeah, we just approved the utility waver for.
I read.
Right.
Okay.
And then America.
It was the other one.
Yeah, I know.
I just didn't know who.
I didn't know Irene's last name.
Any other questions?
Or are there any on that topic?
What are I being asked to take any action tonight?
Or just discussion.
I think it's floating at right now.
It was a trial.
Yeah.
I'm 14.
Resolution to weigh the fees for billing permits
and inspections for the Miami Public School
2016 bond construction projects.
Travels is popping up here.
But I'm going to do a little bit of an introduction.
I'll think you mind.
Yeah.
I want to make it very clear that this is an item that has been
initiated internally by staff, not by the school board.
And not by the schools.
But we're very happy that the bond issue was approved.
And they are getting to work on these schools.
There would be about $9,000 in permitting fees.
It would be paid to the city as part of the projects.
The re-roofing, the additions to the buildings and things such as that.
And I do know that when the election was taken place,
there was a question about, you know, what fees and things like that would
have to be paid as part of this.
And our thought was that the schools are no different than us.
They are, you know, it's hard for them to get money.
And this is something that's overdue.
And we can certainly live.
without $9,000. And that's $9,000. It can go into these buildings. It's just a little bit more
that they can stretch those bond dollars. So what we're asking you for permission is to go ahead
and wave the fees for building permits and inspections for the public schools. Now we'll still do
the inspections. We'll still do everything there. So don't think they get a free ride there,
but we're not going to charge it for it. I think that's a good intergovernmental activity for us.
And our attorneys assured us, we have the right to do that.
The political, there's a state statute that I'll promise to do.
Right, we don't have to put a cap when they use, so it's approximately $9,000.
I don't think it's, I mean, we're just waving. What I thought, not yet. And then I've,
based off what I was given by the schools, which is in front of you, it's kind of outline of what's
going to be done. And I just kind of basically looked at that, gone off that on what our fees are going to be
going to be looking at. And that's, we anticipate that somebody might, how much are we getting up?
That's an estimate. Yeah, yeah, yeah. There may be, I mean, there's,
they're going to have to change orders, things like that. I mean, so it could be,
little less could be a little more. But are there subs still required to have the city? Yeah,
there's subs are still plenty. Yes. Yes. Yeah. Okay. It's just that we're not going to charge.
We can form a form what I understand they hired a construction manager last night.
And the architect is very close to getting the plans finished, so. And this is,
any work involved with the 2016 bond? Yes, project. Yes. Correct. Okay.
It's trying to stretch those dollars. Okay.
I would like to take that back then to watch it. Yes, to wave the fees for permits and inspections
for the 2016 bond issue. And do we have a second? That's like roll call. Thank you.
Lewis. I Johnson. All right. Forster. All right.
Listen. All right. Show. All right. I don't think there's continuation of discussion of the proposed budget.
And you think any other questions, ladies or gentlemen that have come to mind since we were meeting earlier?
I just, to me, it's up to y'all. But I would just ask it during our workshop. We might add this
in this case. There is some questions that I'm happy to. Good idea. So be sure to list out as an agenda item.
Yeah. Next year is our workshop. Okay. Item 16 is new business and you need business dean or anyone
of your own it? Okay. Seventeen is mayor and council community announcements. I have one there. Just so everyone
knows it's summer time. And tomorrow is the last day of school. So I would just make sure staff is aware
and everybody's window out in community. Everybody's heads on swivel because you're going to have to be
entering the ramp. So that being said, the next item that I wanted to make note of is our annual girls
softball is headed off on the 18th going to be played in the National Tournament.
I think you might even be able to stream that, so on.
New school, yeah.
Going in here.
It's all I got.
No, thanks for that.
Thank you, Brian.
OK.
18 is City Manager Communications Dean.
Three very quick ones.
First off, I just want to congratulate Amanda and the CVB for the radio.
I think by all measures, both formal and informal
probably the biggest and best radio they've ever had.
Number of people, number of participants, number of people that have been
in the stands.
I know, Amanda's exhausted, but that had a great job as usual.
And so the radio committee, and just wanted to congratulate them, also we have the
job and blasters here last Thursday.
And the crowd was not as big as we had hoped.
I think it was kind of the first time we did something like this.
And I think we had about 1,150, 160 people in the audience.
But the blasters couldn't have been more pleased.
I was a little concerned about the number of people that showed up.
But their hope point was this expose this team to the region.
And they want to think of themselves as a regional team.
And also a commitment to art, staff, my, my high school and RBI.
But the first thing I've heard when I walked in and introduced myself and from several people in
the blasters is they absolutely love that field.
They said it's one of the best they've ever played on.
And that really says something about what my aim was done for the high school baseball team.
But again, the blasters couldn't have been happier and they're already talking about coming back
next year.
I'll have a couple of people, church, ask me if they're coming back next year as well.
I hope so.
And our hope is that those 150 that were there and had a great time.
I think I saw Jill and Ed Jill's husband for the first time there.
And I think they all had a really good time.
And the hope is that word of mouth next year is going to be a lot more people.
They're planning on trying to do this in other cities and in the four states as well,
which I encourage them to do.
But as I said, we might not have had as many people as we would have liked.
But the ball team couldn't have been happier with my Emma.
I'm very proud of that.
And the final thing is that we were made aware by the Route 66 landing proposal that the
of the board is going to be meeting tomorrow.
And the staffers are recommending funding, they're proposal.
And there are very few proposals that are actually being funded.
A lot of them that have been eliminated.
One is the Oaks.
If you remember, there's one of the South part of Tata did not meet the requirement.
And it's a very rigid numerical requirement system that they have to go through.
So it's not a done deal yet.
The of the board still has to vote on it.
But I think we were all happy with all the hurdles that they had to go through.
That this is one that's being recommended.
And if you'll remember, this is the one that would have scattered infill housing in the
core area of town, plus converting the harvest time church or what I call the Robinson
Building into off-to-part.
So they still have one more hurdle to-
go through, but they did share with us that staffs are recommending
approving that.
So we're very happy about that.
And those are my reports.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
Item 19 is Executive Session for Senator 25, OS 307 B4 for
Prof. Green Cations with the City Attorney concerning
the pending investigation.
Also, pursuant to 25 OS Section 307 E and 305.
Do we have a motion to go into Executive Session for the
reasons listed under Item 19?
I'm going to get motion notice.
And a second?
Second?
Roll, roll, please.
For a start?
Question?
Aye.
Loose, aye.
Johnson?
All right.
Aye.
Yeah, that's what I'm waiting for.
Okay.
We want to get together.
Don't we want to?
Hopefully that means that.
Well, I just saw chair.
There's no chair.
Okay.
We are at Executive Session at 637 BM.
Next item on the agenda is adjournment.
We have a motion to adjourn.
I'll make motion.
And a second?
Second?
Roll, call, please.
For a start?
Aye.
Loose, aye.
Johnson?
Aye.
All right.